Baird Leonard Papers, 1909-1937
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Baird Leonard papers
1909-1937
Leonard, Baird, d. 1941
MS 93
2 boxes (1 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Columnist; Social critic; Poet; and Humorist. Papers contain photographs, bookplates, drawings, scrapbook and correspondence with famous and lesser known writers and journalists. Includes original manuscripts and typescripts of columns, essays, articles, and verse; plus notebooks, reviews and clippings of her articles and columns.
Leola Baird Leonard (known professionally as Baird Leonard), was born 16 May 1888. She graduated from Smith College in 1909 and was a columnist, critic, poet, and humorist for Life magazine (1922-32), The New Yorker (1925), Harpers (1927-29), Judge (1932), and the New York Morning Telegraph (1912-24). She also published a book of poems entitled Simple Confession (1930). Her work was chiefly light and satiric verse and parodies. Her column, "Mrs. Pepys' Diary," a parody on Samuel Pepys with a "jazzy" New York slant, was featured in Life. She married Harry St. Clair Zogbaum. Baird Leonard died in 1941.
The Baird Leonard Papers contain correspondence, writings, photographs, bookplates, drawings, and a scrapbook. The papers also contain correspondence with other writers and journalists, including Frank Bacon, David Belasco, Louis Bromfield, Charles Dana Gibson, Oliver Herford, William Lyon Phelps, Robert E. Sherwood, Sara Teasdale, Hendrik Van Loon, Carl Van Vechten and Carolyn Wells. The writings series includes original manuscripts and typescripts of columns, essays, articles, and verse; plus notebooks, reviews and clippings of her articles and columns. There are also a few photographs,a scrapbook, and the original drawing by Charles Dana Gibson of "Mrs. Pepys" at her typewriter which headed her column.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
Baird Leonard's papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by her sister, Kate Zogbaum Linzboth in 1954 and 1955.
Search Terms
Women--Humor--History--Sources; American wit and humor--Women authors-19th century--Sources; Humorous poetry, American--History--20th century--Sources; Journalism--United States--History--20th century--Sources; New York (N.Y.)--Social life and customs--20th century--Sources; Leonard, Baird, d. 1941
- Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence
  - Adams, Franklin Pierce, 1919, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bacon, Frank, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Belasco, David, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Broomfield, Louis, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gibson, Mr. and Mrs. Charles Dana, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hamilton, Cosmo, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Herford, Oliver, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hughes, Rupert, 1916-17 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hughes, Adelaide Maud (Mrs. Rupert), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Jordan, Kate, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Knox, Rose Markward (Mrs. Charles), 1924 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Liverwright, Horace, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Maxwell, W. B., 1925 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Robinson, Theodore Douglas, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Roche, Arthur Somers, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Sears, Zelda, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sherwood, Robert E., 1918 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Shipman, Louis Evan, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Teasdale, Sara, 1918-21 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Van Loon, Henrick Wilhelm, 1882-1944 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Van Vetchen, Carl, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - White, James Terry, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - White, Mary Cornelius, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Woollcott, Alexander, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Notebooks: for Morning Telegraph and general, undated (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
- Notes on lectures (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Photographs and book plate (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Writings
  - The Book Market, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Mrs. Pep's Diary," 1928 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings and miscellaneous, 1929-31, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Woman About Town," articles, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The Polo Grounder (Hits Pinched at the Polo Grounds), 1914 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Manhattan Monotypes, 1926, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Verses, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Verses--Answers to Famous Questions, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Crazy Quilt, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Scrapbook: reviews and correspondence re: Simple Confessions, 1912-30, undated (Box 2)
- Drawing by Charles Dana Gibson of "Mrs. Pepys" at her typewriter with "Life" (as cupid) looking on (inscribed by artist), undated (Map-case Flat File:)